Developers love freedom, and security teams love control.
How do you give engineers fast, flexible,
and powerful development environment that too without letting
code or credential leak to the personal laptops?
The answer is Cloud Workstation and Cloud Shell.
Let's see how we can do that.
In modern DevOps, developers often need access to the production like APIs,
access to private repos,
and also sometimes they need a local like ID experience. But
when we do it on our traditional laptops,
that creates the risk of source code leak,
security issues like secrets stored locally.
So to answer that, what you can do is you can create a cloud‑based workstation.
Type in the first command.
I'm going to say gcloud workstations cluster, and create the cluster.
Now I'm giving the name of this cluster as a dev cluster.
I need to provide the region, network, and subnetwork information.
And let's say Enter.
Now remember,
when you're going to create the cluster, this is
going to take a couple of minutes, almost 15 to 20 minutes it is going to take,
so we have to run this command and wait patiently.
Now my cluster got created.
If I want to go and see it,
I can come down here onto the Google Cloud and search for workstation.
So let's go to the Workstations, and here under the Workstation,
I can see Cluster management. And inside the cluster manager, you can see
that we have the dev cluster ready and it has taken up all the network and
subnetwork information that I have provided.
It is not that you can only create this cluster from the command.
You can also create this cluster directly from the Google Cloud from here on.
You can just come down here and say Create,
and then you can provide all the information like name,
location, and the network setting, whatever you like to give,
and then you can say Create.
So this Cloud Workstation cluster can be created through the
command line, as well as through here.
Now, as we have already created the cluster,
now it's time to go ahead and set some kind of a configuration for that.
For that, I'm going to again use gcloud command.
Let me say clear here and type in the command.
So the command for creating the Workstations
configuration is gcloud workstations config,
and then you say create and give the configuration name.
I'm giving the configuration name as payments‑config.
I provide the region, cluster.
Remember this is the cluster which we have created in the previous step.
So I'm giving the same cluster that is the dev cluster.
I'm providing the machine type,
saying that when you're going to add the workstation using this configuration,
the machine size of that would be e2‑standard‑2,
and then I'm providing lastly the container image.
So what could be the image of container, that is
going to get loaded in that machine.
So I'm using some predefined image, and let's say Enter.
Now this is also going to take a couple of more minutes
to go and create this configuration.
Now the same configuration you can go back and see from the UI as well.
So you minimize this window,
go to the Workstation configurations, and here you can see
that configuration once this gets added up properly. Right
now it is in the state of updating, so it is yet not fully created.
Meanwhile, that is running behind the scene.
We can go inside this payment config.
That is the configuration. Here you can see that
right now the status is Updating,
but it contains the information that we have provided,
like the cluster name is dev‑cluster.
The machine setting,
it is still updating, and correspondingly, we can add a couple of more
information in this configuration part. And you can also click on Add users
and the permission to that specific configuration.
In fact, you can also create the configuration from here on as well.
You can just say here +Create,
and then you can create the workstation configuration from
here also. And when you do it from here,
you can give further more information,
very specifically. At the time of typing the command,
we might not have given that detailed information,
but here you can set a couple of more information as well.
So if you go back to our terminal,
you can see that it is showing that configuration has been created successfully.
Now, once the configuration has been created successfully,
it's time to create the workstation.
So let's type in one more command for that.
So the command is gcloud workstations and we are saying create the workstation,
giving the workstation name as payment‑ws.
We provide the region and the cluster and the config which we have just
created so that this workstation automatically takes all the properties
that you have set into the configuration.
Say Enter.
Now it will take a couple of more minutes, and then it will create. So
you can see that we've got our workstation ready.
We can come down into our UI part again,
go down to the Cloud Workstations,
and here we can click on this Workstations tab.
And within the Workstations, you can see that we have one workstation ready.
So this workstation right now in the Stopped state,
either you can run a command to start that workstation,
or you can start it from here saying Start.
Now this will also take a couple of minutes to get started and ready.
Now once this gets started and ready,
it will be available for us to directly use it. You will get one URL.
With the help of that URL, you can launch this specific Cloud Workstation.
Now you can see that our workstation is in the Running state.
I can again click on these three dots,
and if I want to see the specific logs related to that workstation,
I can click on Logs, and that will show me all the state it has gone through,
and you can see the entire information.
If you go back again and let's say you want to get into this workstation,
so you have to just simply click on this workstation and on the
top here you can see an option of Launch.
So you can launch this,
or maybe you want to connect to the web app on a specific
port or you want to connect via SSH.
So let's do the connect to the web app, and I got this URL.
What I can do is I can copy this URL and open it in another tab.
Now you will see that we got an entire workstation.
So this is a clean environment, we get it.
I can say let's just open a folder,
and from here I can start doing my work on this newly created Cloud Workstation.
So that will be a clean environment where your developer can
work and everything will reside in this machine rather than on
the developer's personal laptop.
You also get the terminal, click on these three lines,
say Terminal and say New Terminal.
So in the bottom, you get the terminal.
Let me just a little bit expand it.
If you want to install further more items, you can install it from here.
You can just say sudo aptget update.
Now this update gets done, let me do clear,
and then what I can do is I can keep on installing
furthermore libraries like Google Cloud CLI,
maybe kubectl, Terraform, and all I can do it on this specific workstation.
Besides this specific Cloud Workstation,
we also have an option of a Cloud Shell.
Now Cloud Shell is something that is always available,
and lightweight dev terminal.
Although we are already using it since the beginning of this course,
I'll just walk you through it again.
When you go down to the Google Cloud, on the right top corner,
you see a sign for the terminal.
Right now my terminal is already open.
Let me just from the bottom, let me close this window.
So here on the top, you start to again see this terminal option enabled.
You can click on this, and you will get your Cloud Shell.
Now the beauty of this Cloud Shell is that you can
run any command that you want,
and you don't have to install anything specifically.
All your Google Cloud SDK and CLI is already installed here.
In fact, if you want to have that kind of a Visual Studio Code,
you can click on this Open editor and you get in an environment
where you can get an IDE like Visual Studio Code.
This Cloud Shell is given to as a free VM, and it is pre‑installed with gcloud,
kubectl, and Terraform.
It also consists of 5 GB of persistent storage,
and most importantly, it is secure, browser‑based as such,
and it does not require any local credentials.
So that's how the Cloud Workstation and Cloud Shell provide a secure,
scalable, production‑ready developer environment.